All right, welcome everyone. Hello. It
is September 26th, 2025
and we're live in quarterly roundt
number three.
Greetings.
This is Alexandra
and Daniel
and uh we'll walk you through the round
table.
All right. We're a participatory online
institute that is communicating,
learning and practicing applied active
inference. This is recorded in an
archive liveream. So please provide
feedback so we can improve on our work.
All backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and will follow video etiquette
for live streams. You can screenshot
that slide with some helpful permanent
short links. Okay, we are in
the near fall equinox quarterly round
table number three of our year and we're
going to go through some institute level
updates and then highlight a bunch of
projects and then close with a fun
culinary metaphor and look to people's
live chats. So if you're watching live,
write any questions or anything in the
chat.
Okay.
So 2025
short link
is a living entry point for this year's
activity and ecosystem.active
inference.institute is our main living
document. So ton of resources, ton of
places to explore. Let's get right into
the updates.
One of the major activities that we've
been working on with a team over the
last few weeks has been preparing for
the fifth applied active inference
symposium. This is going to be online
though possibly with some in-person
activities around the world and so far
there are about 20 presenters confirmed.
Carl Fristen will be the keynote
speaker. We'll have a bunch of live
streamed sessions. We will have several
workshop and training sessions and a
bunch of pre-recorded presentations as
well. The theme is going to be industry
and all that it means. So if you go to
the symposium short link right now, you
can register as a participant. And also
presenter registration will be open
through the end of October. And we're
looking for any sponsoring organizations
who would like to have that visibility
and make that contribution.
All good.
Okay. Research fellows programs. So
research fellows are affiliated
colleagues at the institute. We now have
six research fellows. JF Cloutier, Anna
Pereira, John Boy, David Bluman, Robert
Warden, and over the last few months, we
have accepted a new research fellow,
a
colleague of of multiple projects here
at the institute, Shaggy Robin, whose
project is the myth of objectivity
hypothesis. And there's a page in the
documentation about Shaggi's work and
link to his paper and previous live
stream at the institute and we are
currently in the midst of another round
of reviews for research fellows.
So check out their work, check out the
program and let us know if you have any
questions.
And we welcome future applications for
research fellows. um which will be
reviewed on a rolling basis uh in the
coming quarters.
All right, on to partnerships. These are
structured relationships between the
institute and other organizations who
are looking to have that kind of a
container/vehicle
for their learning, upskilling,
contributing, however they want to help.
and some board of director colleagues
have been working on this program and
taking a lot of learnings over the last
year and a half or so that we've been
operating it and we'll be updating and
releasing more information on that soon.
We just wanted to here acknowledge our
current partners who are all in
different ways involved and we'll be
helping out with the symposium
organizing sessions. First Principles
First, Newman Games and Lazy Dynamics
and one other soon to be announced
partner organization as well. So if you
would like to be an advocate at your own
organization or you have any other
feedback on the way that this kind of
program can lead to synergistic and
sustainable development in our
ecosystem, absolutely go for it and let
us know.
Okay.
In the third quarter, we continued to
have excellent input and participation
from our very broad scientific advisory
board. So, these are informal guidance
participants.
And one of the highlights of this last
quarter was the previous cycle of
reviews of research fellows and the
ongoing reviews. It really demonstrated
an excellent level of expertise and care
by many of the individuals here and
starts to help reduce our uncertainty
and walk towards a model that's like a
iterated or improved articulation of how
we almost thought it could be when we
set out to be the institute in 2022.
where the board of directors provide
formal guidance and strategy. The
scientific advisory board plays the role
of expert and input and then we the
officers are just boring behind the
scenes administrators who help
coordinate all that and are like the
editor for the reviewer type role that
the SAB members can play. So, at this
time, we will be sharing more
information about next year's SAB in the
coming weeks and months through the
newsletter and everything. But right
now, you could go to the SAB short link.
You could explore any of the cool
projects and contributions that these
individuals are making. And if you are
interested or if you have a
recommendation in somebody who you think
could be good for that type of a
scientific education research nonprofit
area
contributor then the SAB is a great
place to get involved.
Okay.
To our formal roles. On the left side
are Alexandra and I as officers. And on
the right side, we wanted to acknowledge
the board of directors, John Clippinger,
Blue Knight, Alex Vatkin, Daniel
Freriedman, Mike Smith, and Vladimir
Bowen. We had a very good BOD meeting
several weeks ago, and there's a few
good threads cooking. So, it's been
really awesome to see again all those
developments on the formal, the
informal, the research, all these
different things
and we will share more in the coming
weeks, but you can always email blanket
and see what's up. And then just lastly
in this section, the institute is a
501c3 taxexempt nonprofit. You can
always go to the donate short link or
get in contact if you have any other way
that you'd like to support us with your
attention and care and contribution is
priceless as well. So keep that in mind.
And now on to the projects.
Okay, starting with some of the
educationoriented projects that are
happening at the institute.
We slowly iterate and maintain the
ontology, the audiovisisual production
textbook group and journal projects. So
reviewing a few of those and a few of
the other projects that are happening.
All right. First we have the AI
capabilities and alignment project. This
is AICACP
and from the previous round table you
may remember that through the survival
and flourishing fund uh this team with
Adam Saffron, Amelia Tomley, Michael
Garfield, Victoria Clamage, Tyler
Mongan, Zanvang, Hatim El Jazouli,
Amelia Tomley, Nick Haye, and myself.
That project was funded for $270,000
and they reported, "Our team has been
meeting weekly to make progress towards
multiple goals for AICACP.
We are currently finalizing the first
special issue related to our project
focused on world modeling. Planning the
second world modeling special issue,
planning a special issue focused on
agency, developing a podcast involving
authors of the paper that are included
in the special issues. Organizing the
first of multiple workshops focused on
AI capabilities and later alignment. We
have a web page here that further
describes our project and are currently
working on developing a standalone
website which we hope to develop and
launch in the next few weeks and the
short link is there.
Great work,
fun.
Okay. in the textbook group.
We, as we have been doing since around
May of 2022, have been reading through
the 2022 textbook in groups. And over
the last couple of weeks, we have been
closing out this current interval of
activity. Cohort 8 is finishing the
second half of the textbook. Cohort 9
has been working through the first half
of the textbook. We would like to
acknowledge Andrew Pasha for his
excellent and dedicated facilitation.
And as we look to the future of textbook
groups and the educational opportunities
in the ecosystem, we point to the
expected release date of Sanjie Nam
Jooshi's book in March 2026.
That book is going to be called
Fundamentals of Active Inference:
Principles, Algorithms, and Applications
of the Free Energy Principle for
Engineers. Never really looked at it
this way, but it's funny that it's the
principles
of the free energy principle.
Yes.
And we did the sort of alpha/BA
working through this book with Sanjieve
and group at the institute. And we
expect to have a textbook group ready to
roll out as soon as that PDF hits your
inbox or physical paper hits the
mailbox, whichever's first. Um, so we
may still have this 2022 book around and
it's definitely a core artifact in our
literature in our corpus. But as we
start to look to the end of 2025 and
what's on the radar for 2026, we are
quite excited for this comprehensive
textbook to be coming out and we'll be
doing a lot around making this
accessible and applicable and there's
code associated with this book. Sanjie's
a great researcher and developer. So
very exciting for textbooks in general.
I'll just add that as a active member of
the cohort 9 uh textbook group, um it's
just a lot of fun and it's really never
too late to join a textbook group and
learn more and uh just see it from
another person's perspective and uh
yeah, you know, join join the coming uh
cohorts and see what you might find out.
That that helps me see the cover as like
a ferris wheel. It's just it's always
going around. People popping in, popping
off. All right.
The theoretical neurobiology group,
which is Carl Fristen's research open
discussion group, has been continuing to
meet. And the TNB short link has all the
information that you'd like about how do
you participate in these live historical
proceedings and where you can look at
the videos that are uploaded for most of
the presentations as well. So if you
want to see what's happening week by
week in a different format in a
different curation than the institute
live streams and if you'd like to engage
in a very small group special setting
with Carl Fristen and other researchers
then we cannot recommend highly enough
that you participate in the TNB. It's
really awesome and they are out there
one to two times per week. So there will
be a few more meetings in this year and
then I'm sure things will continue next
year.
All right. In audiovisisual production,
we have had a somewhat quiet, calm,
chill quarter. There were nine streams
in the last quarter. Uh at the video
short link, you can find all the 600
plus streams overall. But let's see. We
had mainly guest streams this past
quarter. Guest streams related to the
inner screen quantum active inference
and consciousness, energy based
transformers,
compute crisis and physics- based AS6.
That was an interesting kind of pairing.
Both of them were very energy- based
modeling.
Then active inference and artificial
spin ice that was sort of meta
materials.
co-creative learning via metropolis
hasting between humans and AI co
co-creation and a third way that's
neither supervised nor unsupervised
learning
thermal macroeconomics
temporal cognition and conscious active
inference 2 and then I did a stream on
the start repo called start/here here
and that was about using generative AI
for customized active inference
curriculum and a variety of other
things. So, it's a fun
quarter in production and there is a
clear checklist and a way if you want to
contribute in front or behind the
microphone
to making available and accessible
highquality videos, audios, podcast, all
kinds of things, English language, other
language formats we've done, formats we
haven't done, guests we've had, guests
we haven't had. there's more to do than
not here. So whether you are already
working in audiovisisual production as a
hobbyist or professional or if you kind
of want to explore those skills, this is
an awesome way to build your open-
source portfolio, make a huge permanent
difference.
Okay, going into the research space
in the RX infer project, we have
continued to have weekly meetings. These
have been facilitated by Frasier
Patterson, a PhD student who's working
on RX infer and other things in his
dissertation research. We have continued
the weekly meetings which are sort of
this open space to check in on how has
the package been developing? What
experiments uh and examples have people
been working on? Personally, I've been
working on a fork of the RX infer
examples repo keeping it close and
trying to make some of the examples more
modular. So on the right top side here
is a mountain car example and on the
bottom is a streaming data kind of like
a live streaming situation. So if you're
curious about RX infer or just applied
active inference this is a great place
to check out and there there will be
sessions related to RX infer as well as
other application frameworks at the
symposium.
Okay,
going into the ecosystem projects. So
these are projects that are out in the
periphery or even closer up against to
the institute. People doing their own
thing, learning and applying active
inference in their own way on their own
timeline and filling out the measure
form at that measure short link when
they have a piece of information that
they want to share publicly that we can
put into these quarterly roundts and
into the newsletter. So pretty much when
we're curating that monthly newsletter
or when we're curating the materials for
this quarterly round table, we submit
our own internal measurements what we're
doing in all these different projects
that we want to share and then we look
to the submissions of this form that
other people put in and then we go from
there. So again, if you see something
cool, if you see a bird, if you made a
bird, if you did whatever, put it in
here. And if it's relevant and
reasonable, we would love to share that
work out. So okay, let us review some of
these
projects and their updates over the last
quarter.
Avil uh reports uh significant effort
was invested in the actin for
archaeology paper as part of the escape
project applying the framework that they
developed in a 2024 paper um by Guinan
Carl and Duborg um power ritual and
identity a cognitive study of conversion
to the unification church um to the
study of material culture
And also they're providing mentorship
and support for a PhD application of a
fellow commu community member.
Yes. And I would just add this is kind
of like a classic
SAB scientific advisory board
participation like advancing one's own
research helping out in a professional
way. So thanks Ael and um you know all
these projects.
Okay,
Jesse Gardner and Vladimir Balon report.
We published a perspective preprint
together evaluating directions and
advances regarding the prospects of AI
with regard to agents. The paper's on
archive and the title is is the agent
paradigm a limiting framework for next
generation intelligent systems.
Okay. Then uh JF Cloutier uh from the
symbolic cognitive robotics project
reports, "I am making constant progress
designing and coding a single agent
distributed robotic cognitive
architecture. The static sensor and
cognition actors, the priority bottom
layer of a society mind are now coded
and tested. Work has begun coding the
dynamic cognition actors, all other
abstraction layers. I have updated
detailed accounts of belief acquisition
and policy construction and execution by
cognition actors. All updates are on the
GitHub and the #simcogrootics
uh discord channel.
Thank you to research fellowjf.
It's it's a very fun format to see these
concepts woven through the GitHub,
through the Discord discussion, people
popping in asking questions. It's it's
really fun. It's a great project and
it's really getting there.
from the project active inference
for built environments and cooperative
systems project. Ivon Mattelkin reports
the white paper has been released on
GitHub.
The first three blog posts as part of
the research have been published on
Substack.
We are on the first phase of the
research which is a problematization.
Okay. Thank you Ivonne.
Um and here we have an update from
interns Harshel Shaw and Satiyaki Mitra.
Um
very fun uh drone related work. Um we
developed a hierarchical active
inference model for autonomous drone
navigation based on affordance theory.
The architecture uses an action policy
filtering mechanism based on a latent
suitability state. The system was
applied to waypointbased navigation and
is now transitioning to real hardware
with lidar and depth camera. Preliminary
tests in May showed positive results and
we plan for more extensive testing with
the finalized model and hardware
integration. Complete hierarchical
active inference implementation with
affordance-based action filtering
involves Julia Rx infer.
complete implementation in Microsoft
AirSim and positive preliminary tests
and significant progress towards more
extensive testing in AirSim and
hardware.
Significant progress in in transition to
real quadcopter hardware. Um and
excitingly poster presentation accepted
for IY 2025.
Quite an update.
Cool. And we'll just use that to
highlight that in just about two three
weeks in Montreal, Canada will be the
sixth international workshop on active
inference.
We're not involved in the organizing
there, but just wanted to shout that
out. And many uh of our colleagues will
be joining there. So enjoy everybody who
who goes there. hope that there's a lot
to learn and to do and looking forward
to to some afteraction there.
And the last of these
project measurements, researchers Ryan
Buchanan and Kyle Flynn reported, "We
provided publication for a theory half a
decade in the making, made progress on
onlogical questions, and published an
interdisciplinary artifact,
multimodality and its relation to
construct object theory. Okay.
So now we are completed with the project
level measurements.
Um,
if you are watching live, write some
comments or questions in the live chat
and we'll read them. Otherwise, we'll
just have kind of two, three slides just
talking a little bit about what could be
and a few ways that we're thinking about
all that is happening.
just trying to expose a little bit of it
and use that as our our sense making and
our communication out to you all at this
time for for your updating and
engagement. So what do you see on this
slide?
Well, this is our classic uh ant
foraging
uh metaphor. Um,
we're foraging through uh space and time
and acknowledging uh you know what we've
seen and found and uh what we're looking
for and uh blazing a trail for anyone
else to join us and uh you know
co-create the pheromone trail. Um and uh
you know speculative directions is
always what we're uh sort of cooking in
the background.
We're looking for um exciting
opportunities and keeping an open
uh open mind and open contact for uh
people to suggest uh propose funding or
projects
um and other co-creative
opportunities for the institute.
Yes. And the
equation 2.6 Six expected free energy
epistemic and pragmatic value. This is
really the question for you. What what
are you reducing uncertainty about? What
are your known unknowns?
What and how are you open to the unknown
unknown? What's useful for you? What
aligns with your utility or preferences?
And you could be reducing uncertainty to
achieve pragmatic ends. You could prefer
to learn. So all these different
combinations
and hopefully we are there to support
that and help the ecosystem flourish so
that you can find what's epistemic and
pragmatic for you. Um we get to see and
engage a lot of windows into the range
of people who are out there. Some very
quiet and in the background, some very
loud in Discord or through other
channels, and some in academia and
research institutions, others that are
not. So many different life stages and
uh locations. So we try to keep it
really broad at the top level and also
want to have those capacities to to zoom
in. Okay.
And then here's one kind of cooking
related slide. So um chapter six in the
textbook
as those who have read will know is a
recipe for designing active inference
models. And year after year it dawns in
the kitchen and in the classroom how big
the difference is between reading a
recipe or writing one of your own and
actually putting that cooked dish or
menu on the table. So, as we're kind of
hanging out and thinking about all this
and what's the institute's role, here's
just a few of the the threads that we
follow is like even if we have a recipe
book or really the recipe for the
recipe,
there is distance to travel that could
be a implausible distance to travel. It
could be right there. And we think that
with tech and infrastructure
development, we will facilitate these
travels. But that doesn't get rid of the
distance itself to travel from creating
a recipe or getting one off the shelf, a
open- source or proprietary recipe to
making that dish in your home kitchen or
maybe you're doing recipe development or
you're writing speculative culinary
fiction. You're writing recipes that
aren't intended to be cooked or they're
not able to be prepared by you at this
time. And there's all these different
useful things that cooking can do as
well. So that helps us think like okay
we are akin to a culinary training
institute. We are training and raising
awareness around various epistemic and
pragmatic delights giving you a
accessible rigorous applicable honest
authentic understanding of what are
those delights?
What do we like about them? How are they
made? what's in them, what's cool or
different about them. And the institute
then is this place for convening, for
connecting, learning, advancing and
upskilling in this culinary culture of
service. So to serve active inference,
it's a cookbook. And this brings
together a sort of to serve active
inference cookbook cookbook cookbook.
And also, of course, let them cook
because you are the ones who will be
cooking. We also cook. We want to help
all be fed and cook. And if you want to
do dishes, that's great, too. And acting
for a serve. That could be insert your
own. What is the point of all of this?
Learning how to cook and for what so
that you can serve what? That's what
it's about for you. And if that journey
leads you to be a board of directors
member or some other contributor at the
institute, fantastic. If it's just a
glancing interaction that helps you do
your thing,
whatever that is, also fantastic. That's
what we're here for. Then there's
serving our professional community and
our niche. So these are the epistemic
paths and garden beds that are upstream
of making that high reliability or that
critical infrastructure or that
educational material for active
inference. the upstream contributions
that relate to attention and resourcing
to to stepping in to volunteering for
peer review to mentoring uh a student or
somebody entering saying yes. saying no.
Knowing where where you want to and how
you want to say yes and no to reaching
out to people and connecting and and
having there be a dense fabric and and
richness to our actual community of
colleagues and peers to review others
work. Some people produce a lot, some
people read a lot. And it's not that
every single comment needs to get thrown
into the same potluck, but it's awesome
when people feel like their work is
being seen, being recognized, and and
acknowledged even with an emoji.
and holding all that in this spirit of
professionalism and respect so that we
can have these different dialogues,
these different multimedia, trans media
interactions and be reviewing what we
have done, what others have done,
curating and and
gardening the past and making the
present something that moves into the
future in a healthy way. And then in the
sort of most technical sense of serving
API requests for those who really want
to see it get down to brass tax and what
does it mean to apply active inference
at some point there's going to be
something that serves up some service to
your um
recipients.
So that's just one fun way that that we
try to think about what we do as sort of
like
restaurant
administrator
hosts also sometimes the pref chef and
all of that. But all these different
roles are it's just one metaphorical
frame to transpose what we really do
into.
It's a fun one though. So,
um, we will dwell on this last slide for
just a few minutes in case anyone else
has any live chats. I'll I'll read these
and then we'll read the
um live chats that we have. Then we'll
see if there's any other comments or any
other reflections to make and that will
be it for today. Okay. So this slide has
been copied over possibly even since the
very first pre-active inference lab
uh live stream the teamcom streams back
in 2020
and they are what might a good
understanding enable what are the unique
predictions and implications what are
the next steps for free energy principle
and active inference what are the
preferences of this work
what are you still curious out. Okay,
I'll read some of the live chats, then
add anything you want, and then we'll
see if there's anything else to add.
Okay, love evolve says, "Hey,
yinyang symbol, spiral, chili pep, sun,
shooting star, taste masters. Thank you
to Love Evolve." Morgan wrote, "Really
appreciate the quarterly updates as well
as the newsletter." Thank you. It it's
um it's definitely appreciated. It it's
a great learning experience.
It gives a a rhythmic
seasonality. There's months and there's
quarters where more and less and
different happen, but we have done this
every month and we've done it every
quarter. So, we always get something
together. And um
it
this quarter had a very comical and uh
frantic but
uh enjoyable feel of us in our in our
PhD days preparing for a qualifying exam
um in the in the hours in the minutes
before the committee presentation. um
except of course presenting permanently
publicly in this fashion but nonetheless
very fun and and reminiscent.
Um I'll flip briefly for our vision
model colleagues to through all the
slides from the beginning and then we'll
look if there's any comments.
So if you're here, you're in it. If you
heard this, you know, you can send in a
measurement. If you want something
shared publicly, you can send an email
to blanket. If you want to just enter
into a communication,
you can engage with any of the people or
projects listed. You can search them
independently or you can follow the
trails from the links and documentation
we have. You can step in, you can step
out, you can do your own thing, you can
learn and apply and weave and zigzag
within all of that. you can stay updated
and bring in your own
uh
ways of working and thinking about the
situations that you find yourself in. So
Sasha, any last comments and then I'll
read the chat.
Um well to echo the uh earlier an
analogy uh it is like preparing a
committee meeting update. Um, so it's
fun fun to do that. Uh, but it's more
important than that because we're
curating and uh presenting and combining
everyone else's work um at the
institute. And so it's an honor and a
privilege um just share uh all the work
that people are doing and uh can't wait
to do it again next quarter frantically
as ever. Okay, I'll read some of the the
comments in the chat and we'll just
we'll just see if um if there's any
um fun topics that come up from there.
All right, Jim Freda wrote, "I am always
surprised not to see the application of
active inference to the big problems of
life like mismatch." And then I asked,
"What do you mean mismatch?" And Jim
wrote, "Evolutionary mismatch,
environmental mismatch."
You know, if you expect it to be there,
put it out there. Definitely mismatch in
terms of prediction error or discrepancy
or fitness is a major topic. Not always
discussed in terms of mismatch,
but often in terms of surprise,
predictive error, error signal, um
fitness. So maybe you can add any other
comments you have, but but
If you feel like it's a syntactic or a
semantic opening,
amazing. Write that paper, put in the
measurement, and we will be right here
in just a few months sharing that.
Michael Lennin wrote, "Beautiful work.
Your stigmic example sparks action.
Thank you for holding up light for
others." Thank you. I raise a mason jar
of dilute coffee to you, Michael.
Jim laughs will do. Okay, great. Yep.
Well, we'll just wait a few more seconds
if anyone else has a comment, but um
yeah, we're 3/4 through
the year. It's going fast.
Um let's look at the symposium website
just to
show its current state.
I'm going to fix the cropping.
Okay. So, if you go to the symposium
short link, it'll look like this.
Here's the link to register for the
symposium.
And here's the
program.
So
the registration link right there
that'll take you to a
KOD form.
If you select no, you don't want it
shared publicly, then we're not going to
share it. If you do want to share it
publicly, we will include it in a
open-source GitHub repo/symposium
that we started last year. So, it will
develop like a personalized curriculum
for you and maybe make some connections,
maybe form some research teams. Um, and
also just help connect you with others
who might be curious about your
background. It asks fun questions here
like,
and these are things that we seek to
know whether you want to share it
publicly or not, but these are fun
things to reduce your own uncertainty
about and to
see what other people wrote. like the
responses that people put in these
fields are incredible and I I it's a
whole symposium
even without the um Fristen keynote and
and 20 presentations and trainings
just reading what people write to this
following set of questions that I'll
read is its own education. So the
questions are what would help you learn
and apply active inference for example a
resource tool or community development.
What would be useful for you in the
symposium? Pragmatic value. What would
be interesting or informative for you to
learn from the symposium? Epistemic
value. What is your background and prior
works? Feel free to provide as much
information and links as you like. What
are the biggest hurdles or challenges
facing active inference research and
application? How did you hear about the
symposium? How could active inference
applications make impact in 2026? Think
big.
How are you applying active inference?
What domain and stage? Any other
comments or questions?
So, if you want to be
participating in this, the proceedings
will all be available.
if you want to be part of the
interactive sessions though and um
there's a ton here. So that's the
symposium which hopefully between now
and uh one month from now we will also
see a few new presenters submit.
Um
yeah
I think we've said what we needed to
say. So, thank you,
Upcycle.
Thank you for the gifts. Wrote, I'm
looking forward to the symposium. Thank
you for your generosity, Upcycle.
It's been awesome. So, everybody, see
you next time. See you in the inbox.
See you in the kitchen. See you later.
Bye bye.